Guide to the Chris D. Howard Papers, 1972-1983 RL.11669
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Chris D. Howard Papers
1972-1983
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Howard, Christopher, 1961-
Grabarek, R. Wense
McKissick, Floyd B. (Floyd Bixler), 1922-
Pearson, Conrad Odell, 1902-
Semans, Mary Duke Biddle Trent
RL.11669
4 Linear Feet
Oral history and research collection forming the basis for Duke University undergraduate Chris D. Howard's 1983 senior honors thesis, including research notes and recorded interviews with political and civil rights leaders in Durham, North Carolina.
Arrangement
Chronological
Biographical / Historical
Chris D. Howard was an undergraduate at Duke University when he interviewed prominent Durham political and civil rights leaders as part of his senior honors thesis in 1982 and 1983. He earned his M.S. and Ph.D. degrees in political science from MIT. In 1993 he joined the faculty of the College of William and Mary, teaching and authoring books and articles on social policy in the United States.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Chris D. Howard Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1985.
Collection Overview
Collection contains Howard's research material for an honors thesis. There are fifteen envelopes of research notes, chronologically arranged. The notes concern the early history of Durham, from 1865 to the 1960s, and events related to the struggle for racial equality in Durham, N.C. The collection includes a set of 29 audiocassettes of oral interview recordings conducted by Howard, with local individuals such as Wense Grabarek, Vivian McCoy, Floyd McKissick, Conrad Pearson, Jake Phelps, Ben Ruffin, Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans, and others who participated in, or witnessed this struggle. There are notes and outlines of these interviews (both those on cassette tapes and others conducted by telephone) and a list of persons interviewed by Howard, Also included are copies of two papers, written by other Duke students in 1972 and 1978, about the Civil Rights Movement in Durham, N.C. during the early 1960s. Forms part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture at Duke University.
Audiovisual materials; Oral histories (document genre); Audio recordings.; Southern States; Civil rights -- North Carolina -- Durham; Durham (N.C.); Race relations; Civil rights; Durham (N.C.) -- Social conditions; African Americans -- Civil rights; Durham (N.C.) -- Race relations; African Americans -- North Carolina -- History; Grabarek, R. Wense; McKissick, Floyd B. (Floyd Bixler), 1922-; Pearson, Conrad Odell, 1902-; Semans, Mary Duke Biddle Trent
- Interviews, 1982-1983; 4 linear feet
  Conditions Governing Access
  A portion of the audio in this collection has been digitized and audio files are available on request. Analog audio that has not been digitized requires digitization prior to access. Contact Research Services for further information.
  Arrangement
  Chronological
  Scope and Contents
  Thirty-one oral history interviews with 23 respondents. Telephone interviews were not recorded but notes and partial transcriptions for these can be found in Folder 1 of box 5.
  - Interview 1, Mary Trent Semans, 1982-10-04
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0001)
    - WAV audio file, 00:45:41 (Digital-materials RL11669-SET-0001, Object RL11669-CS-0001_01.WAV)
    - WAV audio file, 00:35:13 (Digital-materials RL11669-SET-0001, Object RL11669-CS-0001_02.WAV)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 2, Ben Ruffin, 1982-10-07
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0002)
    - WAV audio file, 00:36:39 (Digital-materials RL11669-SET-0001, Object RL11669-CS-0002_01.WAV)
    - WAV audio file, 00:36:10 (Digital-materials RL11669-SET-0001, Object RL11669-CS-0002_02.WAV)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 3, Ruth Dailey, 1982-10-08
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0003)
    - WAV audio file, 00:31:11 (Digital-materials RL11669-SET-0001, Object RL11669-CS-0003_01.WAV)
    - WAV audio file, 00:31:12 (Digital-materials RL11669-SET-0001, Object RL11669-CS-0003_02.WAV)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 4, Vivian McCoy, 1982-10-12
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0008)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 5, Vivian McCoy, 1982-10-19
    - Original audiocassette, 1 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0009)
    - Original audiocassette, 2 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0010)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 6, Vivian McCoy, 1983-04-01
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0011)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 7, Lew Hannen, 1982-10-29
    Telephone interview - no recording available.
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 8, Conrad O. Pearson, 1982-10-29
    - Original audiocassette, 1 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0012)
    - Original audiocassette, 2 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0013)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 9, Conrad O. Pearson, 1982-12-16
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0014)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 10, W.G. Pearson, 1982-10-18
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0015)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 11, John Edwards, 1982-10-26
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0016)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 12, John Edwards, 1983-02-23
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0017)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 13, Jake Phelps, 1982-11-01
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0018)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 14, Jake Phelps, 1982-11-04
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0018)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 15, Jake Phelps, 1982-11-11
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0019)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 16, Allston Stubbs, 1982-10-08
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0004)
    - WAV audio file, 00:45:42 (Digital-materials RL11669-SET-0001, Object RL11669-CS-0004_01.WAV)
    - WAV audio file, 00:14:47 (Digital-materials RL11669-SET-0001, Object RL11669-CS-0004_02.WAV)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 17, Floyd McKissick, 1982-11-30
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0007)
    - WAV audio file, 00:47:28 (Digital-materials RL11669-SET-0001, Object RL11669-CS-0007_01.WAV)
    - WAV audio file, 00:32:20 (Digital-materials RL11669-SET-0001, Object RL11669-CS-0007_02.WAV)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 18, Floyd McKissick, 1983-03-03
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 19, Floyd McKissick, 1983-03-29
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 20, Reverend Grady Davis, 1983-02-01
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0020)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 21, George Parks, 1983-02-03
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0021)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 22, Pat Cusick, 1983-02-05
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0022)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 23, Quinton Baker, 1983-02-05
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0023)
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0024)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 24, Wense Grabarek, 1983-02-25
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0025)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 25, Dorothy Swann, 1983-03-03
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 26, Lacy Streeter, 1983-03-06
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 27a and 27b, Jocelyn McKissick, 1983-03-15
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0005)
    - WAV audio file, 00:46:09 (Digital-materials RL11669-SET-0001, Object RL11669-CS-0005_01.WAV)
    - WAV audio file, 00:46:06 (Digital-materials RL11669-SET-0001, Object RL11669-CS-0005_02.WAV)
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0026)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 28, John Stewart, 1983-03-16
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0027)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 29, Thelma Kitheart, 1983-03-18
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0028)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 30, Watts Carr, Jr., 1983-03-25
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0006)
    - WAV audio file, 00:30:53 (Digital-materials RL11669-SET-0001, Object RL11669-CS-0006_01.WAV)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Interview 31, Major Worth Hill, 1983-03-29
    - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL11669-CS-0029)
    - Handwritten interview notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Research (Box 5)
  Contains notes on interviews, research index cards, and copies of papers written by other Duke students in 1972 and 1978.